<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short description of Antichrist vnto the nobilitie of Englande, and to all my brethren and contreymen borne and dwelling therin, with a warnynge to see to, that they be not deceaued by the hypocrisie and crafty conueyaunce of the clergie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852078</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17381</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20307)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17381)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 306:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short description of Antichrist vnto the nobilitie of Englande, and to all my brethren and contreymen borne and dwelling therin, with a warnynge to see to, that they be not deceaued by the hypocrisie and crafty conueyaunce of the clergie</title>
                  <author>Old, John, fl. 1545-1555, attributed name. aut</author>
                  <author>Gwalther, Rudolf, 1519-1586, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By E. van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1555]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes erroneously attributed to John Old and to Rudolph Walther.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>The ascription may arise from confusion with John Old's translation of Rudolf Gwalther's "Antichrist" which is wrongly described in Dict. Nat. Biog. as another edition of this work--Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17381:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17381:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſhort deſcription</hi> of Antichriſt vnto the Nobilitie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and to all my brethren and contrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men borne and dwelling therin, with a warnynge to ſee to, that they be not deceaued by the hypocriſie and crafty conueyaunce of the Clergie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ioh. 10.</bibl>
               <p>He that is of God, heareth the worde of God.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:17381:2"/>
            <p>OH Lorde God / although ſuche lordes haue dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs / as knowe the not / yet graunt that we may hope only in the / and kepe thy name in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For beholde the Lorde will go out of his habitation and viſite the wickednes of them that dwell vpon the earth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.</note> He wil diſcouer the blood that ſhe hath deuoured / ſhe ſhall neuer hyde them that ſhe hath murthered. Muſter you and gather you / muſter you and gather you? Take your counſaill together. Yet muſte your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill come to nought. Go in hande withal / yet ſhall it it not proſper / except Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel / <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.</note> that is / God be wyth vs. For ther is no prudence / ther is no wyſdome / ther is no counſaill againſt the LORDE. ☞☜</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17381:2"/>
            <p>THere is nothing more peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe (right honourable Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) ne yet more pernitious and euell to the Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mans religion, then ſo to be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, poyſoned, and blinded in his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and iudgement, that he eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth &amp; iudgeth euel in the ſtede of good, errour in the ſtede of veritie, cloked ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtition in the ſtede of Chriſtes true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, painted hypocriſie in the ſtede of godly vertue, manifeſt and open ydola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in the ſtede of true worſhipping of God, mens dreames and traditions in the ſtede of Gods moſt holy lawes &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men cuſtome (long tyme vſed of our forfathers) in ſtede of a ſure grounde and firme foundation of our chriſten faith, And finally to accepte and take Antichriſt, the Man of ſynne, and childe of perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as Paul nameth him) in the ſtede of God and of Chriſt. Who neuertheleſſe is moſte contrary to God, and moſte hatefull enemye to Chriſte, in all his doctrines, workes and conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Such erronious, blinde, and corrupte iudgementes, God (by his Prophete E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay) pronounces accurſed ſayeng:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.</note> Wo be to you that ſaye good is euil, and euill is good: light is darkeneſſe, and darkeneſſe is light. &amp;c. Alſo the Apoſtle S. Paul
<pb facs="tcp:17381:3"/>
fearing like errour and corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, to come to the Corinthes, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the wicked doctrine of ſubtile and falſe preachers,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> exorteth the Corinthes to beware of deceauers, ſayeng: I feare that it come to paſſe, that as the ſerpente deceaued Eua thorough his ſubtiltie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo your wittes ſhoulde be corrupted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſingleneſſe that you had towarde Chriſt. For falſe Apoſtles (ſayeth he) are deceatfull workers, and faſhion them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues lyke vnto the Apoſtles of Chriſt. And no merueil for Sathan him ſelfe is chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an Angel of light? Therfore it is no great thing, though his miniſtres faſhion them ſelues lyke as they were the miniſters of rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Whoſe ende ſhalbe accordinge to their workes.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo (right honorable lordes) I can not but feare leſt your vnderſtandin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and iudgementes, be now corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted drawen and caryed awaye from the ſimplicitie and purenes of ſincere vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandinge and godly iudgemente which late you had of Chriſte, thorow the crafty perſuaſions, deceatefull and falſe illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Antichriſt, that hath tranſfigured hym ſelfe in to the faſhion of an Angell of lighte. For I am not ignorante that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17381:3"/>
now the monſtrouſe beaſte Antichriſte, Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vicar general in earth and all his adulterous generation of vipers, that be his falſe Apoſtles, moſt ſubtile and crafty deceauours, and the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious enemies of God and Chriſte, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe not daye nor night with falſe lyes, colo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red with cloked hypocriſie, and deceat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and flatteringe perſuaſions, to decea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the Quenes mageſtie and all you, my lordes, of hyr moſt honorable counſaill, wherby they might draw hyr highnes &amp; all you, from the godly and moſt pure knowleage, which you had in litle tyme paſt, receaued of Chriſte, in to their fylthy Puddels and vayne inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions, that they of their owne braynes (without any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of holy ſcriptures, haue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to reuiue and to ſtabliſh the vſurped power and bloody kyngedome of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in this realme. By whoſe falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trines, all the people of this realme ſhall be drawen from God, and from our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte to truſt in moſt vayne and deceatefull vanitie.</p>
            <p>But if, your lordſhips wolde both waye and ponder, that not only God by his holy prophetes, and Apoſtles, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chriſt hymſelf admoniſheth and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth you and all men, to beware of falſe
<pb facs="tcp:17381:4"/>
preachers and of craftye and ſubtile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauers: your Lordſhips wold be moch more circumſpecte and well ware, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that not only the Prophetes and A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles, but alſo Chriſt him ſelf, (to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ought to gyue credence) hath war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you to beware of ſoch deceauers.</p>
            <p>And namely becauſe this deceate ys not a manifeſte and playne deceate eaſely to be perceaued, and knowen of al men, but ſo craftly coloured and ſubtylie painted with deſſebled perſuaſions, and of ſoch as ſhall come euen in the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, and of his holy church. And therfore they ſhal deceaue many, ſayeth Chriſte. Sainte Paul alſo ſayeth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> In the later tymes ſome ſhall departe from the faith, geuinge eare to the ſpirites of erroure and doctrines of deuylles.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> And the ſame ſayeth that hereſies muſt neades be, that the proued and godly maye be knowen. Sainte Peter alſo ſayeth: that there we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wicked Prophetes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2</note> as there ſhalbe fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe maſters amonge you that ſhall bringe in ſectes of perdition, that ſhal denie the Lorde that hath boughte them. Alſo S. Iohan ſayeth.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4</note> Antichriſte is come, and that ther be many Antichriſtes. Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe that the Prophetes of God, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, and his Apoſtles, haue this certenly-and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17381:4"/>
diligently admoniſſhed and warned you and all men, of falſe preachers and of leenge maſters that departe from the fayth / and bringe in ſectes of perdicion / and of ſoch that will come in the name of Chriſte / <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24</note> lyke as they did preach his true doctrine / which neuertheles preach their awne dreames and the doctrines of deuils, denyeng the lorde that brought them / and in all thinges folowe the ſpirites of errour.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> It behoueth your Lordſhips, and it is the parte and moſt bounden dutie of euery Chriſten man, di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligently to ſearch out theſe falſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, lyenge maſters, and to laboure ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly, to knowe which be the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of deuils, and ſpirites of errour, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the admonition and warnin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the Prophetes, of Chriſte / and of the Apoſtles geuen to them, that they maye circumſpectly eſchew and auoyde them that they be not deceaued by them and their doctrines.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in the reigne of Edwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the ſixte of famoſe memory, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his honorable counſel, ther was a doctrine preached and religion recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in this realme of Englande, which now is reiected and baniſſhed as a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the deuyll, and as hereſye, and
<pb facs="tcp:17381:5"/>
falſe religion: And a nother doctrine and religion receaued, to the former religion and doctrine, directe and manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore wil doubte, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the firſt doctrine and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the later doctrine and religion rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aued be the truer and better to be folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed. I will commende vnto youre god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembraunces (right honorable lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) not ſuch doctrines as any new wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters call, of their awne heedes, falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, and doctrines of deuyls, or the doctrines of lyenge maſters. But the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me doctrines that Chriſt and his Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les expreſly call falſe doctrines, and the doctrines of Deuyls. So that your lordſhips nor any other ſhall haue any iuſt cauſe to be ignorante what be the doctrines of deuyls, and who be wycked preachers, and lyenge maſters, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſecte of Antichriſt, &amp; who alſo is the heed Antichriſt.<note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſerue Antichriſt and yet do not knowe hym.</note> Although doubtles righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te honorable lordes) I well perceaue the multitude of the worldly people ſo pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of God with blindnes and hardnes of hearte, that all though they with all dyligence ſtudie and obedience, dayly do ſerue Antichriſte, the greateſt aduerſary of God and of Chriſte: yet do they not knowe nor vnderſtande hym to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17381:5"/>
chriſt, nor do perceaue his crafty illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, his hypocriſie, and diſguyſed faſhons. So that except a man conſider &amp; beholde hym aſſuredlye by the light of Gods worde, he ſhal neuer vnderſtande, eſpie, nor perceaue hym, although he had a ſubtyle and pregnant witte, as clere and wel ſeyng eyes, and as craftye a brayne as euer had man. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyſed vnder the colour of holynes: Yea and that in the name of Chriſt, &amp; vnder the pretence to condemne al falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious doctrines and hereſies. Which thing all Chriſten princes, and all other good men, wilbe moſt diligent and glad to do. But herin he moſt ſubtilie and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefully begileth al men. For he and his adulterouſe generation will chalenge to him and to them autoritie &amp; power only geuen to determe, diſcerne, and to iudge what is hereſie, errour,<note place="margin">Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in the name of hereſie, conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth the trueth</note> &amp; what is falſe doctrine. And by that meanes, be the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine neuer ſo true and godly (yf it ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de any thinge againſt his vſurped power, his pryde, his profite, his vngodlye decrees and lawes made in generall Counſeils, and other his falſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked determinations, and iudgementes) he will condemne it for hereſie.</p>
            <p>And he that preacheth it, hym will he
<pb facs="tcp:17381:6"/>
accurſe, callyng him the enemie of God, and of al the holy church, a ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, not worthye to dwell in any comen wealth. But yf Emperours, Kynges &amp; other ciuill gouernours &amp; rulers, wolde examin his doctrines, and trye them by the light of Gods heauenly worde, and proue all his other procedinges, how they agree with the ſame. They ſhould then ſone perceaue, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; knowe, that he himſelfe (although he calleth him ſelfe the head of the church and Chriſtes vicar vpon earth, the ſucceſſour of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) yet ſhould they fynde and proue hym, to be the head Antichriſt, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heretique, the man of Synne, and childe of perdition: And al his ſectes, to be the ſectes of perdition, that departe from the fayth, that alſo attende to the ſpirites of errour, denyeng the Lorde that bought them.</p>
            <p>But for as moch (right honorable lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) as no man can wel put any diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie betwixt two extreme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries, except he perfitly vnderſtande and knowe bothe the contraries, I will firſt deſcribe and ſet forth vnto your good lordſhips, Chriſt (who is contrarye to that wicked Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt) according as the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.</note> which (as Chriſt ſayeth) beare true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17381:6"/>
of hym. And then I will alſo paynt in his lyuely colours, that Arch heretike Antichriſte, that extreame contrarye to Chriſte. But no nother wyſe, then Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the holy ſcriptures haue reueled and euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly expreſſed and declared hym. So that the one contrarye compared and ſet nere to the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, ſhall expreſſe, declare and ſet forth the other, more euidently, playnlye, and more aparauntly.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt, Chriſte is as muche to ſaye,<note place="margin">Chriſt.</note> as annoynted, (as Ieſues Chriſte was of God the father) not with oyle &amp; creame coniured of our Biſhoppes, but with the holy Ghoſte, who in the holy ſcriptures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44 <hi>and.</hi> 88.</note> is called the oyle of gladnes: by whome God enlighteneth, enſtructeth and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his holy Churche, of the which he hath appointed and authoriſed, Chriſte to be the Supreme head, Kinge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.</note> Hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſhop, and euerlaſting Prieſt. Who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng equall with God his father, dyd vouchſafe of his mere mercy &amp; good wil, to deſcende from heauen, &amp; toke on hym our vile nature: not forſaking his diuine nature, but ioyning them together, (both natures remayning not diminiſhed, hurt or altered) &amp; became a perfite man, in all
<pb facs="tcp:17381:7"/>
natural miſeries like vnto vs excepte on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 5.8 <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</note> And euen then when we were his enemies he reuyued vs, and offered hymſelf to God his father vpon the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, as a ſacrifice to be ſlayne for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of oure ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10</note> By which this his only one ſacrifice ones performed for vs, (not for a litle ſeaſon, but for euer) he hath made holy and perfite them that be and ſhalbe made holy and perfite. And by this meanes he hath reconcyled vs to God his father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.</note> pacifienge his fathers wrath, that then was againſt vs, thoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh his bloodſhedinge, and paynfull death. And he that was without ſynne, became a ful,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> iuſt, and perfite ſatiſfaction for oure ſynnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.</note> And hath taken awaye the curſe and condemnation of the lawe, delyueringe vs from the cruell curſe and iudgemente therof. And after thorow his awne power, he ouercame death, and aſcended to heauen, where he continueth oure aduocate, mediatoure, and only ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure from oure ſynnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10.</note> Oure onely waye and doore by the which we muſt enter into eternall ioyes. To whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to geue the honoure and thankes for our redemption from ſynne, hell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 43 <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.</note> and death euerlaſtinge: And therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to obeye and ſerue hym all the dayes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17381:7"/>
of oure life in holines and righteouſnes, accordinge to oure callinge. Herin ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I deſcribed and declared to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable lordſhips oure redemer and only ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, and his only offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and benefites moſt mercifully exhibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and done to vs. By the which deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, your Lordſhips maye / with moch more facilitie &amp; eaſe, haue certayne &amp; ſure vnderſtanding &amp; knowlege of Antichriſt, the other extreme contrary to Chriſte.</p>
            <p>This Antichriſte muſt not be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded and taken (righte honorable Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) for one naturall man,<note place="margin">what is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> that by nature is as all other be, a miſerable ſynner, or that he ſhuld be a certen wicked perſone, that ſhuld be begotten betwixt a Freere and a Nonne, or betwixt a Monk and a Nonne, according to olde wiues fables and winter tales. But this name Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, is the name of a miſterie and offi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce perteininge to a miſticall bodie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the principall miniſter is called the chief Antichriſte, as all the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the ſame faction, miſterie and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, be alſo Antichriſtes. All which rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue power, autoritie, and office, from their heed Antichriſte, that in al his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, maners, and lyuinge, is mere con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary to Chriſt. For euen as that congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb facs="tcp:17381:8"/>
is the miſticall body of Chriſte, wherof he is the ſupreme heed, that hath receaued the true and ſincere preachinge of the law and of the goſpel, and lyue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the preachinge of the ſame, and alſo haue the ſacramentes duely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred vnto them, accordinge to Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes inſtitution of the ſame:<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte.</note> Euen ſo is that malignaunt church and congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the miſticall bodie of Antichriſte, that hath not amongeſt them the true and ſincere preaching of the Law and of the Goſpel, ne yet the ſacramentes dulie adminiſtred vnto them, accordinge to Chriſtes inſtitution of them, ne yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the practiſe of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nor of the primatiue church, nor the ſame can be content to lyue according to the rule and doctrine of Gods heauenly worde: nor ſuffer any other to lyue accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge to the ſame: but will compell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with tormentes to receaue a new religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that muſt conſiſte other in vayne thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges which be of no commoditie or profit to any man ether ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: or els it is manifeſt wicked and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to Gods holy worde. And firſt touchinge their vaine thinges, and deed ceremonies of their religion, that be of no commoditie or profite to any man
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17381:8"/>
excepte onlye to the ſluttiſhe ſecte of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. I note all their popiſhe tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of confirmacion of yonge children with oyntinge of oyle and creame, and with a ragge knitte aboute the necke of the yonge babe, the chriſteninge of bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, the halowinge of oyle and creame, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> halowinge of churches of churchyardes, of chalices, of veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, of aultares, of aultare clothes, of ſalte, of bread, of fiere, of aſſhes, of water, of candles, of palme ſtickes, Iudas bels with candels blowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out at the ende of euery Pſalme and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, crepinge to the croſſe with egges and apples, diſpelinge with a white rod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, waſſhinge of aultares. Of all which thinges the holy ſcriptures commaunde not one to be done, although in this chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Antichriſt they be ſtraytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be vſed. And yet I know no wiſe man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil or can prayſe the comoditie or profite that cometh therof to any man, but only to the prieſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. &amp;c. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be offred vnto hym. And altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh ther riſeth not any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite other ſpiritual or te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral to any man: yet as I haue ſaid, they be ſtraytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to be obſerued / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 12</note> That which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only take hede do to the
<pb facs="tcp:17381:9"/>
Lorde, Putth on nought therto.</p>
            <p>Not withſtandinge which commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demente / becauſe Antichriſte wold part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet forth his awne nature and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is, to be contrary and diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to God and Chriſt, he hath erected theſe new holy thinges, neuer of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. And therfore as they be not of God, ſo be they of no commoditie or profite to any of the people of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">why An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note>But yet ther is ſome conſideration wherfore Antichriſte hath commaunded theſe vayne thinges to be done. One is, that he wold haue his filthy generation to be had in eſtimation of the worldly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, becauſe that they haue receaued ſoch holines from his holy fatherhood, that they maye ſanctifie and make holy, that God hath halowed allready, lyke as the thinges of Gods creation were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cientlye halowed thorowe his eternall worde wherby he created them. Exalteth not he himſelf aboue God, honorable lordes, that taketh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym to adde holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to that which God hath ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly halowed? Be not theſe his halowin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Gods creatures a neceſſary point perteininge to the vocation of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall paſtoure / that hath cure and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of ſoules? Or be they not neceſſary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17381:9"/>
thinges to be done of a Chriſten man / towchinge his vocation and dutie to be done towardes God and towardes his neighbour And although they be worthy rather to be laghed at and mocked / yet by theſe his vanities he occupieth the tyme hat ſhuld be ſpente in the inſtruction &amp; teachinge the people in the lawe and the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Moreouer by theſe, as alſo by many other their doinges / they declare their di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligente cure and ſtudye that they haue to obeye Gods commaundement geuen to them to inſtructe and to teach the people Gods worde, that leaue the goſpell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preached and occupie the heartes and mindes of the people with ſoch trifles and vanities. But becauſe theſe vayne thinges do not ſufficiently reuele this wicked Antichriſte and his ſecte. That he may be knowen of all men, I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende to youre memories (honorable lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des) ſome of his falſe doctrines: Not ſoch as I of myne awne brayne, call falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and the doctrines of deuels, and of ſoch as departe from the fayth, and be lyeng maſters, and geue eare to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of erroure: But ſoch doctrines as Chriſte and his Apoſtles note to be the doctrines of deuels, and of ſoch as by
<pb facs="tcp:17381:10"/>
the ſame doctrines ſhal deceaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſhall cauſe many to folow the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of erroure. So that euery man that heareth ſoch doctrines preached, maye boldlye ſaye, that the preachers therof be falſe preachers and ſectes of perdition, that they be the adulterouſe generation of Antichriſt, that theſe many yeres haue deceaued and bewitched the world.</p>
            <p>And although Chriſt and his Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les haue manifeſtlie declared, and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſet forth to the world the ſayd doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines to be the doctrines of deuels and of them that departe from the faith, and the very ſelfe ſame doctrines wherby An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichriſte and his filthy ſecte ſhulde dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue many Yet ſoch hath ben the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the worlde, that they can not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande nor perceaue thoſe doctrines, to be the ſame wicked doctrines, wherof, Chriſt and his Apoſtles admoniſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; al men to beware: not only becauſe he coloureth his doctrines with falſe payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gloſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> but alſo becauſe the world lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth darkenes moare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lighte, And alſo to verifie Chriſtes wordes of prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie to be truely fulfilled in them ſaying: I am come in my fathers name and you re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue me not.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iaon.</hi> 5.</note> But yf a nother ſhal come in his awne name, him wil you receaue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17381:10"/>Now touchinge the falſe doctrines of Antichriſte Sainte Paul ſayeth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4</note> The ſpirite manifeſtly ſheweth that in the laſt tymes, certen men ſhal departe or go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the faith, attending or geuing eare to the ſpirites of erroure and doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of deuels, prohibitinge to mary, and commaunding to abſteyne from meates, that God hath created to be receaued of them that beleue and know the trueth, with thankes geuinge. By this doctrine of ſainte Paul manifeſtlye appereth (ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lordes) that the forbiddinge of mariage is the doctrine of deuels. For God in paradiſe firſt ordeyned mariage, ſayenge: It is not good for man to be by hymſelfe alone. Let vs make to him a helper to beare hym company, &amp; ſo forth as it appereth in the texte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</note> Conſideringe that God ſayde: It is not good for man to be alone, doutles it is not good general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be alone without his helpe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 45</note> And the Prophete Eſay curſeth all them that ſpeake againſte their maker. Noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore durſt be ſo bold to forbidde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to any people excepte only Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and his fluttiſh and ſhameles ſecte, which euer be againſte God and Chriſt. Alſo becauſe it was not good for man to be alone without his wife in the ſtate of
<pb facs="tcp:17381:11"/>
innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie: It is not now good but moch worſe to be without a wife, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man is falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſynne, beyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe more frayle &amp; prone to ſynne. And therfore that man that hath not the eſpeciall gifte of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and will lyue alone, &amp; not take a wyfe. The ſame not onlye contemneth God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des mercyfull ordinaunce made for man in the ſtate of innocencie, but alſo deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Gods louinge benefite and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prouyded for the infirmitie of man, wherby he might auoyde fornication, &amp; other wicked luſtes forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to Sainte Pauls doctrine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> To auoyde fornication, let euery man (exceptinge not prieſtes) haue his wife, and euery woman (exceptinge not vowaſſes) haue hir huſbande. And becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe mariage is Gods ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull remedye prouided for all men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat haue not the gift of chaſtitie: It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good for euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the gifte of chaſtitie to haue a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, namely becauſe it is Gods mercyfull prouiſion and ordinaunce prouided for the helpe of man, and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the holy ſcriptures by Gods holy ſpirite, where no euil thinge can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            <p>And alſo the ſame ſtate of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17381:11"/>
in Chriſtes religion is prayſed of the Apoſtle, ſayeng: Maryage is honorable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</note> &amp; the bed not defiled. Chriſt alſo appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge the ſame eſtate in that he was bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of a virgin in mariage,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> and not of a virgin out of mariage.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> And alſo Chriſte hym ſelfe in his godly preſence honored matrimonie with a great miracle done in Cana, where he turned water in to wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Abraham the father of all beleuers, and other the patriarkes and Prophetes had lawful wiues that were not diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, nor was no impedimente vnto them, but that they had the ſpirite of propheſie &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faruoure of God. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then ſhuld oure vnlerned prieſtes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe to marye wiues ſpecially becauſe all men perceaue by their lyuinge, that they haue not the gifte of chaſtitie? But for ſo much as Paul ſayeth, honorable lordes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3</note> that all thinge (namely of Gods creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ordinaunce) is pure and good to them whoſe conſciences be pure and good. All me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that knowe any thinge in the holy ſcriptures knowe and certenly beleue, that yf oure Antichriſtian prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes were pure &amp; cleane towardes God, his ordinaunce of matrimonie wold not be forſaken of them. But for as moch as by the reſidew of their conditions and
<pb facs="tcp:17381:12"/>
qualities, many thinke them to be ſoch as Peter writeth of,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> that haue eyes full of adulterie and of the inſatiable luſte and offence, &amp; ſo defiled with filthy luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. To our Engliſh prieſtes, godly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie is nother pure nor cleane, and therfore are they vnworthy of chaſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, becauſe their conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pure nor cleane. And then be they ſo caſt of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God that they can not iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge chaſt matrimonie good for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh they can not denye, matrimonie to be Gods ordinaunce, which can not be euill to a good man. And alſo they know that as good men, as any that the holy ſcriptures prayſe, were maried, &amp; had both wiues and childerne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An obiecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note>But to this they ſaye, that matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is godly ſo that it be by ſoch as maye laufully mary. But becauſe they haue made vowes to lyue ſole and vnmari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they ſaye, they maye not take any wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of their owne. But I deſyre them to ſhewe me whether God requireth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſoch vowes to be made by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.</note> And alſo I require of them to ſhew me with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out any diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> whether they wold haue made any ſuch vowe, yf it were not for to be apte to haue a benefice? And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, which maketh lawes to fil
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17381:12"/>
hell / by his moſt wicked decrees hath ordened that euery Prieſt that ſhuld be apte to receaue eccleſiaſticall promotion ſhuld be with in ſoch orders,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> that it ſhuld not be lawfull for hym to marie a wife, therfore make the prieſtes their vowes.</p>
            <p>But for a conluſion (righte honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lordes) ther is no prohibition nor for biddinge of mariage made to any perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes but only to prieſtes and voweſſes. Douteleſſe therfore that prohibition of mariage made to them, ys the ſelfe ſame doctrine of deuels that Paul ſpeaketh of. And their vowes be wicked, becauſe the vowes that they make be proude vowes, that they can not re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der to God, and ſoch as they oughte rather to aſke of God, yf he wold geue them. And therfore foliſh vowes be they, that diſpleaſe God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.</note> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſte ſayeth. And if, your Lordſhips, wold wel conſider, waye, and po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der how moch adulterie, fornication, deflowringe of virgins, murder of infantes, and of maryed men, whoredome and the fylthie ſynne of buggery haue be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row theſe foliſh &amp; vngodly vowes of ſole lyuinge, &amp; prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of matrimonie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to prieſtes &amp; voweſſes, I thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your lordſhips, nor any chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe, other iudge or ſaye, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this
<pb facs="tcp:17381:13"/>
forbiddinge of mariage, is the ſelf ſame doctrine of deuels wherof Paul ſpeaketh As the ſame doctrine wherby the Deuel hath greatlye, and will maynteyne and fill his kingedome. Beware therfore, my good Lordes, of one of Antichriſtes wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doctrines. And note well whether ye haue any in youre Engliſhe clergye that teache that doctrine, and ſtobernly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the ſame And knowe ye them to be Antichriſtes diſciples. And although all the heauens crye out vpon them, and al the earth wondereth at their abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable whoredome, adulterye and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet be oure prieſtes permitted and ſuffred: nay rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, to make ſoch wicked and foliſhe vowes, therwith to mocke the people, that they ſhuld not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their wiues, doughters, nor wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruantes, becauſe, they ſaye, they will haue no nother wyfe but our Lady.</p>
            <p>But Englande can not be ignoraunt of the multitude of their whores and baſtardes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> How this agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls doctrine, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs not to eate with ſoche, iudge you, my Lordes, that ſhuld ſe it reformed. And for your owne honoures prouyde that adulterie maye be puniſhed with the ſame puniſhement that God ordened adulterye to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17381:13"/>
Do you doute whether God did erre in iudgement? Yf you do not thinke iniquitie in God, Wherfore do ye not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hym in iudgement, that can not erre nor commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de any vnrightuouſnes.</p>
            <p>Sainte Paul (right honorable lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) ſetteth forth a nother doctrine of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, the abſtinence from meates in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes and dayes, and for conſcience ſake: ſuppoſinge the meate to be propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and vngodly, and againſte Gods wil and pleaſure to be eaten. Soch abſtinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce from meates Paul calleth the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of deuels, becauſe it is mere contrary to Chriſtes wordes, and the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For meate, ſayeth Paul, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs not to God,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.</note> nether yf we eate be we the better, nether yf we eate not be we the worſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> For that which entreth in to the mouth defileth not the man: but that which procedeth out of the hearte, ſayeth Chriſte. Alſo Sainte Paul exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all men that they regarde not ſoch ordinaunces made by men, lyke as the ordinaunces made by God, ſayenge:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collo.</hi> 2.</note> Let no man trouble youre conſcience aboute meate and drinke. Wherfore, if you be deed with Chriſte (ſayeth he) from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces of the world, whic as though ye yet lyued in the world, are ye leed with
<pb facs="tcp:17381:14"/>
man traditions? Touche not, taſt not, handle not. All which periſhe thorow the veraye abuſe, after the commaundement &amp; doctrines of men. Which thinges out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlye haue a ſimilitude of wyſedome by ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; humblenes, &amp; by hurting of the body, &amp; in that they do the fleſhe no worſhip to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nede therof. S. Peter alſo thought it not meete for hym to eate cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten meates that were forbidden in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes law to be eaten, as thinges that were vncleane.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> To whome in a viſion was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer geuen, that he ſhould not ſaye that thinge to be comen and vncleane that God had purified, thorow his eternall worde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.</note> It is therfore good, ſayeth Paul, to ſtabliſh oure heartes in grace and not in meates which profited not them that walked therin.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note>Doutles, honorable lordes, Sainte Paul wold not haue commaunded gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we shuld eate of all kinde of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come to be ſolde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhambles, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge no thinge what they be, for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake, yf it had not ben lawfull by Gods lawes to eate of all kindes of mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and that in all tymes and dayes ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be eaten temperatly, for the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the bodie, and not for wanton luſt to pleaſe the fleſh, and alſo eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with out
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17381:14"/>
offence of the weake brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes geuyng for the ſame to God that feadeth al thinges But who (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable lordes) hath forbode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe fleſh mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and whit meates to be eaten in Lent &amp; other preſcript tymes? Euen he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath vſurped power to make offences &amp; ſynne of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which God nor his Apoſtles, taught to be ſynne or offence. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e S. Paul warneth you to beware, &amp; to marke them, &amp; decline fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. For ſoch ſayeth Paul,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> ſserue not our Lorde but their belies. And by pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wordes &amp; bleſſinges they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce &amp; begyle the heartes of innocentes.</p>
            <p>But wherfore hath our holy father made reſtraint of meates to be eaten in certayne tymes for conſcience ſake, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of them that he boſteth to be his predeceſſours? Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he might ſet forth his vſurped po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. And alſo that (as S. Peter ſayeth) he might make marchaundiſe ouer vs in couetouſnes.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> For money he will geue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to eate what you wil, &amp; to do what you will. And therfore all his lawes made of reſtrainte, &amp; forbiddyng of thoſe thinges that God lefte free, are but a playne arte and crafte deuyſe made to begyle the people of their money. This, moſte honorable Lordes, I haue ſette
<pb facs="tcp:17381:15"/>
forth two of Antichriſtes falſe doctrines not after myne awne fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſie, but as Paul nameth them the doctrine of deuels, that you might not be any furder deceaued by the preachers of them. And alſo that you maye aſſuredly, certifie youre conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that al they that preache and defende the ſame doctrines, ben vnfaynedly Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes diſciples, which be ſpirites of erroure, that haue departed from the faith: or els the Apoſtles doctrine is erro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nious and falſe: But that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be true. Alſo oure maſter Chriſte, admoniſheth vs to beware leſt any mand deceaue vs. For many ſhall come, ſayeth Chriſte, in my name ſayenge:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24</note> I am Chriſte, &amp; ſhall deceaue many. Who is he that cometh in Chriſtes name ſayeng, I am Chriſte? None doutles,<note place="margin">who be they that ſaye they be Chriſt.</note> but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſurpeth to hym Chriſtes office, power, &amp; holynes, which no man doeth but the Romiſh Antichriſt and his ſluttiſh ſecte. Euen they that vſurpe abſolute power geuen to them to remitte and to forgeue ſynnes to the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vſurpe Chriſtes power and place.</note> whiche is the onlye power, grace and office of Chriſte, and not of any man. Wherfore that man that vſurpeth vpon hym that office of Chriſte, is the very ſame that ſayeth: I am Chriſte, that is, ſo anoynted and authoriſed of God,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17381:15"/>
that I haue abſolute power geuen me from God, to forgeue ſynnes, as Chriſte hath. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſoch maner of ſpeaking all his filthy ſecte, ſittinge in their who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh confeſſions, booſt them ſelfes that they ſit in Gods ſtydde and rowme to for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geue the ſynnes of ſoch as confeſſe their ſinnes to them, ſayenge in their falſe ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolutions in a tonge that the confeſſed vnderſtandeth not. By the authoritie of Peter and Paul, and by the authoritie to me committed I forgeue the thy ſynnes to me confeſſed? But nether Peter, ne yet Paul, did forgeue ſynnes by their awne authoritie, grace or power, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the preaching of the goſpel.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</note> As Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ſayeth: ther is no nother name vnder heauen geuen vnto men, nether is ther a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other by whom we muſt be ſaued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10</note> but the name of Ieſu Chriſte. For to hym all the prophetes beare witnes (ſayeth Peter) remiſſion of ſynne to be had thorowe his name. Alſo, ſayeth Paul, be it knowen vnto you men and bretherne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 13.</note> that thorow this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (meaning Chriſte) remiſſion of ſynnes is preached, and that by hym all that beleue are iuſtified from all thinges from the which ye could not be iuſtified by the law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. For he is the lambe of God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:17381:16"/>
awaye the ſynnes of the people / ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ioan baptiſte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</note> And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſayeth the Angell to our lady,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 1.</note> that he ſhall ſaue his people from their ſynnes. Wherfore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the authoritie of Peter / nor of Paul, ne yet by any abſolute autoritie to them committed, excepte by the autoritie of preachinge of the goſpel to the people, that trulie repente, beleuinge conſtantly to haue remiſſion of their ſynnes by the deeth and bloodſhedinge of Ieſu Chriſt, hath other biſſhop or prieſt any autoritie to forgeue ſynne.</p>
            <p>Lamente therfore (my Lordes) the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate of this realme, conſideringe that there can be no remiſſion of ſynnes geuen, but onlye thorow the preaching of the goſpell, which none of oure prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes thorow all the realme do practiſe in their whoriſh confeſſions, nor yet know they what is a goſpel, moch leſſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they preach the goſpell. Halas, by what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes do theſe beaſtes of the bely geue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes to the people, when they ſpeake not one worde of Chriſte that the confeſſed doeth vnderſtande or perce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue. But in their abſolutions they geue penaunce to the confeſſed, faſtinge certen dayes, lyplabour in ſayenge of thinges they vnderſtande not, maſſes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17381:16"/>
to be ſayed, and almes to be geuen for the ſatiſfaction of their ſinnes. Thus bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye they Chriſtes paſſion, and deeth, and bloodſhedinge, which only be oure ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for oure ſynnes. And no nother can be. And although God, by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Eſai, commaundeth all paſtours that haue the ſpirituall charge of ſoules,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 43.</note> to ſhew vnto his people their ſynnes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: Crie and ceaſe not. Lyft vp thy voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce as a trumpet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 58.</note> &amp; ſhew my people their ſynnes. Notwithſtandinge this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of God geuen to all them that haue ſpirituall charge of ſoules, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte myndinge to ſhew to the world, that he thinketh him ſelfe wiſer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and that he can make more godly and holſome prouiſion for ſoule health then God, hath made a law that all people of euery kinde once in the yere at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leeſt, ſhal confeſſe and ſhew their ſynnes to their awne Paſtour or curate. God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that the paſtoure ſhall ſhew to the people theyr ſynnes. But Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte commaundeth cleane contrary, that the people ſhall ſhew their ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to their curates. By theſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the people for the moſt parte beleue that they haue remiſſion of their ſynnes, becauſe they haue nombred their ſynnes
<pb facs="tcp:17381:17"/>
in to the eares of their confeſſoure. Or els for what cauſe ſhulde we confeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our curates? For euery man knoweth what is ſynne, &amp; that he ſhalbe damned yf he forſake not his ſynne, yf the prieſtes execute the commaundemente of God geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Eſai.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai</hi> 58.</note> But the ſimple people thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke verely that when the curate pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth a certen ſownde and voyce of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ouer their beedes which they thinke is an abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſinnes, although they vnderſtande not one worde what he ſayeth, yet beleue they that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that he ſpeaketh hauinge his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vpon their heedes haue vertue and power, to forgeue to them their ſynnes: euen becauſe the prieſt ſitting in Gods ſtede (as they thinke, and as the prieſtes boaſte them ſelfes to do) pronounceth and ſpeaketh them. Wherin all be dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aued lamentablye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aſſured meanes wherby e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man maye haue remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>But doutles, he that earneſtly repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his ſinfull life, fully mynded neuer after to returne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſteth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly to Gods promiſe made of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes to hym, for the paſſion &amp; deeth of oure ſauioure Chriſte / the ſame hath remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſynne althouth he neuer nombre them in to the eare of any preiſt. And then yf he fealinge and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauinge
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17381:17"/>
true, repentaunce and faith in his hearte, will reſorte to any prieſte to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue abſolution and remiſſion of his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, wherof he is aſſured by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame declareth hymſelf to miſtruſt Gods promiſe made to hym of remiſſion of his ſynnes, and then is he an infidele, that by no meanes can haue remiſſion of his ſynnes. And if he be not fully mynded to forſake his former euill lyfe, and neuer to retorne to the ſame againe, then can he not haue any truſt to haue remiſſion of his ſynnes, becauſe that is promiſed to them only that for euer forſake their ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And therfore, if he mindeth not to forſake his ſynnes, he goeth in vayne to his curate to haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſynnes. And if he repenteth his ſynnes and bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, as I haue ſaid, then doeth he euyll to fatch remiſſion of his ſynnes, wherof he is aſſured already by Gods promiſe to be forgeuen. And therfore his goinge to his curate to be confeſſed is veraye vayne and a poynte of infidelitie.</p>
            <p>Oh that the curates of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, wold theye and obſerue Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, geuen to them by the mouth of his prophete Eſaia. But that will they neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But their maſter Antichriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes wyll they deligently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beye,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:18"/>
although they bringe no commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſpirituall or temporall to any man, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge to their fylthie paunches. Euery man maye well perceaue, wherfore they be ſo gready to holde and to maynteyne this whoriſh confeſſion,<note place="margin">Th cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why the clergie ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne auri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</note> and authoritie to heare teſtamentary cauſes &amp;c. Ouer &amp; beſydes that they prouide for them ſelfes in their confeſſions, where they maye be ſped of a whore or two, all the yere after. Yet by theſe their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the chiefe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt kepeth his ſluttiſh ſecte of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in eſtimation with the comen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces they ſitte as God, and execute Antichriſtes office, that is to fill hell with ſoules. And ſo in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions be euer ready to worke ſedition and treaſon againſt both Emperoure kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, and al other gouernours, of that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, realme, and dominion, that ether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth or ſtriueth with their holy father Antichriſte, or ſpeaketh againſt his vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power, his falſe and craftie deceated wicked doctrines, wherby he ſeduceth &amp; begyleth all men for the moſt parte: lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with a falſe confidence and fayth, to haue remiſſion of their ſynnes, becauſe they declare them to his filthy generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſerpentes. And by theſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes innumerable ſoules be le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17381:18"/>
to hell. And moch ſedition and treaſon is wroughte, wherby moch bloodſhedinge and murther is broughte to paſſe to the vtter ſubuerſion and deſtruction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Realmes. As the laſt ſedicion ſtirred vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> North, in Somerſet ſhire, &amp; De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhire, and in other partes of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, be moſt miſerable monime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and witneſſes. And this is not their only co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men practiſe practiſed with vs in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de: but alſo the like practiſe, was practiſed with the Princes of Germany, that will neuer ſuffer their treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be out of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s memory.</p>
            <p>Wherfore this whoriſh confeſſion, wherof procedeth ſo moch euyll and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe to all realmes, which alſo bringeth no profite with it, but ſeduceth and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyleth many, ought to be baniſhed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, although they ſaye, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not well gyue medicine, or plaiſter, that ſhalbe holeſome or profitable, excepte they alſo know the particuler diſeaſe and grief Which anſwere oure holy father hymſelf deſproueth. For he geueth cleane remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a prenaet a culpa, that is from peyne and ſynne, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that neuer ſhewed their offences to hym, and healeth all ſickeneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſores, with this one plaiſter, that is, all that be truly ſory and penitente for
<pb facs="tcp:17381:19"/>
their ſynnes, and be confeſſed to a prieſt haue cleane remiſſion. As for faith in our ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte, it forceth not: ſo thou be confeſſed, it maketh no matter whether thou beleue in Chriſte or no. And yet without Chriſt are we all for euer: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiles damned.</p>
            <p>Why do ye, right honorable lordes / ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit this blaſphemous doctrine, of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes without faith in Chriſt. All that be truly ſorry for their ſynnes, enten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge thorow Gods helpe / neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torne to the ſame, and put their truſt and faith in Chriſtes blood for the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſynnes, haue a generall pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them by God hym ſelfe, by his promiſe, though they neuer come to prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes eare, which is a ſure bull, nor ſealed with lead, but with the bloodſhedinge of Ieſus Chriſte. And therfore, if oure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh prieſtes wolde truly preach the law to the people openly, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld they ſhewe the people their ſinnes, accordinge to Gods commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, and geue them the generall plaiſter, that is, they muſt vtterly forſake their ſinnes, and truſt to Chriſtes ſatiſfaction made for the ſame, This maye they do without cariſh confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion. And this is the only true waye to forgeue ſinnes, and of it ſelfe ſufficiente.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17381:19"/>
Awaye therfore with this blaſphemous care confeſſion, and compell youre prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes to preach the law and the goſpel. And ſo maye, youre lordſhips, auoyde many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls and moch wickednes that enſueth this whoriſh confeſſion.</p>
            <p>And, good my Lordes, beware of them that ſaye, I am Chriſte, that is, ſo anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God with grace that euery man maye haue of me, the ſame benefite that they may haue of Chriſt. For they that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſo in the name of Chriſte, ſayenge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24</note> I am Chriſte, ſhal deceaue many ſayeth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, who can not ſpeake vntruly.</p>
            <p>Beware therfore, my lordes, of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Antichriſtes falſe doctrines and practiſe.<note place="margin">A nother of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes falſe doctrines.</note> A nother falſe doctryne of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte is that he hath inuented and erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the new ſacrifice to be made in the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolotrous Maſſe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of the quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and of the deed.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2</note> By the which ſacrifice they make marchaundiſe of mens ſoules for money. But for as moch as Chriſt hath offred hym ſelf vpon the croſſe to God his father, and become for vs a perfite,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>He.</hi> 7. <hi>et.</hi> 9</note> whole and ſufficiente ſacrifice for oure ſinnes, ones for euer, wherwith he hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye oure ſinnes. By what meanes can oure falſe ſacrificers / with their falſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice made in their ydolotroſe maſſe (neuer
<pb facs="tcp:17381:20"/>
commaunded of God to be made, for the ſynnes other of the quycke, or of the deed) take awaye oure ſinnes. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideringe that Paul ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10</note> where is remiſſion of ſinnes there neadeth no forther ſacrifice to be made for ſinnes, but Chriſte with his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one ſacrifice made to God his father for vs hath taken awaye oure ſynnes, as all the holy ſcriptures beare manifeſte wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. And in the articles of oure crede we confeſſe the ſame. Wherfore this ſacrifice made in the ydolotrouſe maſſe, is moſt wicked and ſinfull, &amp; can not by any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes take awaye oure ſinnes: but is one of Antichriſtes falſe craftes and ſubtile deuiſes therby to maynteyn his ſluttiſh ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration of infideles, to lyue ydly, proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and lecherouſly. And by this their falſe ſacrifice made in their ydolotrouſe maſſe, they robbe Chriſt not only of his honour of oure redemption, and of the thankes dew for the ſame: But alſo they make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to haue a falſe confidence and truſt, to haue their ſynnes to be taken awaye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their falſe ſacrifice made in their maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes. Wherin they be lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tably deceaued. And alſo they robbe vs of oure money, &amp; be the ſelfe ſame robbers that Chriſte ſayeth do deuoure widowes houſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the coloure of longe prayers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>Marc.</hi> 12.</note> and alſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17381:20"/>
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> make marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dice of oure ſoules in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2</note> Theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe not Chriſt to be come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the fleſh, &amp; denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde that bought them.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame ſacrificers, righte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable lordes, take vpon them to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatours and aduocates with God for the people: not for loue,<note place="margin">An other of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> as one man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to praie for an other. But theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediatours and aduocates will not praye but for money. That the como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe maye be verified in them. Where is no pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, ther is no Pater noſter.<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of all thinges moſt ſpirituall. And no man can praye truly, except God teach hym,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 6</note> As it appeareth by the Apoſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſired Chriſt to teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to praye. And alſo, Paul ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> we can not praye as we oughte to praye. Therfore, if our clergies ſacrifices and prayers were ſpirituall, as in dede they be but veraye liplaboure and moſt deceatful bablinges, they ſhuld committe Symonie, for takinge for a spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual office a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral rewarde. But mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neye &amp; all other thinges be ſpiritual when<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they medle with them. They in them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes be ſo spiritual. But mediatours, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocats, wil they be, although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt is our only mediatour &amp; aduocat as it appereth Ioan. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;. 17. &amp;. 1. Tim. 2. and. 1. Iaan. 3
<pb facs="tcp:17381:21"/>
Yet will oure wicked prieſtes vſurpe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the only office of Chriſte: to be me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatours and aduocates. And therby, ſaye that they be Chriſte. But beware of them, honorable lordes. For Chriſt biddeth you beware of them. For they ſhal deceaue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ſayeth Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Beware therfore of a nother of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes falſe doctrines. All chriſten men be bounden to beleue that oure ſauioure Chriſte in his naturall body is aſcended in to heauen, and ther ſitteth on the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hande of God the father, acccordinge as both Peter and Paul haue taughters.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 3. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.</note> And accordinge to oure come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crede. But Antichriſte, and his adulterous generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of infideles haue taughte a nother doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine ſayenge. Here is Chriſte and there is Chriſte. But none ſaye here is Chriſte and there is Chriſte but theſe Maſmon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which ſaye that they (thorow their ſpeakinge of foure wordes, <hi>ſcz,</hi> this is my body) do make Chriſtes body of bred, ther to be really and bodely preſente vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery altare, in one inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, that thei might offer him once againe for a ſacrifice, made for money but not for ſinne. This doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is to be moch ſuſpected to be a falſe doctrine, becauſe that Chriſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you not to beleue them, that ſo teach
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17381:21"/>
or ſaye. And Peter ſayeth that he is in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, and that the heauens ſhall there reteyne hym, vntill all thinges be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Conſideringe that he in his bodely pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence is in heauen, and his bodie is lyke to oure bodies in al naturall thinges, except onlye ſinne. And oure bodies can not be in diuerſe places at one tyme therfore nor Chrifles body ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in diuers places at one tyme. Wherfore, good my lordes, be not any more ignoraunte who be falſe deceauers, wicked prophetes,<note place="margin">Chriſtes body is in ſecrete pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, that is in euery pixt.</note> and lienge maſters the natural broode of Antichriſte The ſame ſecte ſayeth, that Chriſt is in ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cret places, which be all they that ſaye, Chriſtes natural body is in euery pyxe, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginge ouer euery altare, beware of them. For Chriſte ſayeth that by theſe wordes they ſhall deceaue many, Which doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes our Engliſh prieſtes dayly do preach.</p>
            <p>Now I will reherſe a nother of his falſe and wicked doctrines,<note place="margin">Yet a falſe doctrine.</note> inuented only therby to maynteyne a nomber of ydle harlottes, and to lead innumerable ſoules thorow a falſe fayeth and vayne truſt, in to hell. This is his doctrine of purgatorie the pyke purſe of all Chriſtendome. And although the holy gooſte ſayeth / that by mercy and ſayth ſynnes be purged: Yet
<pb facs="tcp:17381:22"/>
Yet hath this Antichriſt fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de out a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Purgato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye.</note> which he calleth Purgatorie, therin to punyſh ſoules, vntill other he, or ſome of his marke muſt make a ſacrifice for his ſoule in his ydolotrous maſſe. But it were no good policie to truſt to moch to their ſacrifice becauſe ther is no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therof made in any place of the holy ſcripture. Nor yet is it wiſdome to truſt moch to their prayers, becauſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete ſayth, that the prayer of the wicked is not wel hearde of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 108.</note> but rather to ſynne. Wherfore it is beſte for a chriſten man to truſt vnto Gods mercy, and not to popiſh ſacrifices nor prayers, which be nother mercy nor faith. And we be ſure that nother the mercy of God nor faith in Chriſte, be in the Popes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute where it pleaſeth him. Wherfore he can not purge ſoules, neither of their ſinnes nor of the peynes dew for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, by Gods iudgemente. It belongeth only to God to purge ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſinnes. As the prophete ſayeth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.</note> No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his brother, nor make agreamente for him to God, for it coſteth more to redeme their ſoules, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye muſt let y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alone for euer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.</note> Chriſte ſayeth, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth, hath now eternal lyfe, &amp; is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heire w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte, to whome God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17381:22"/>
remiſſion of ſynnes frely for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope ſhall do him to moch wronge, to poniſh him for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if he were a true vicar to God &amp; Chriſte, he wold not ſo cruelly poniſh his maſters childern nor louinge ſeruantes.</p>
            <p>But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye not truſt vnto this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh purgatory, wherof ther is no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made in the ſcriptures. Let vs reſorte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures wherin we may he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a ſure hope of a true purgation of oure ſinnes. S. Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeth.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</note> If we walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lighte eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue we felowſhip w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him: And the blood of Ieſu Chriſte his ſonne clenſeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſinne. Here maye all Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if they walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lighte of Gods worde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſtes blood purgeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al their ſinnes. But many perſons (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more it is to be lamented) ſo walck in the darkeneſſe of ſinne, &amp; truſt to haue helpe thorow ſacrifices made, &amp; maſſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can neuer come to Purgatory, but go aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly to hel, wher no purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne can be: becauſe Chriſtes ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth not, is alre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures ſaye: where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree falleth there he ſhal lye, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be at Eaſt, weſt, North, or South.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:17381:23"/>Be not therfore deceaued, honorable lordes, nor truſt to this falſe doctrine of purgatorie, that ſinnes ſhuld be purged with fyre. A Chriſten man wold not put fyre in the ſtede of Chriſtes blood, where with oure ſinnes be purged only, As Paul ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1.</note> Chriſte is the brightnes of the glorie of his father, and veray yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of his ſubſtaunce, bearinge vp all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, with the worde of his power, that hath in his awne perſon purged oure ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. Excepte, therfore, oure holy father will proue himſelfe to be the natural ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of God, euen Chriſte hymſelfe, he pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth not oure ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 1.</note> It is Chriſte that ſo loued vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he waſhed vs in his hearte blood ſayeth Sainte Iohn.</p>
            <p>Conſidering, right honorable lordes, that I haue called to youre memories cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of Antichriſtes falſe doctrines, which I of myne awne herd do not name to be doctrines of deuels, doctrines of lyenge maſters, and of ſubtile deceauers, and of them that departe from the faith, but out maſter Chriſt and his apoſtles (to whom all chriſten men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> geue credit) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them ſo, &amp; the preachers of the ſame falſe Apoſtles, and ſoch as with their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe doctrines ſhall deceaue many. Of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte admoniſheth you to beware,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17381:23"/>
and the Apoſtle deſireth you to marke &amp; well to take hede of them and to decline or departe from them For they ſerue not Chriſt the Lorde, but their belly.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 16.</note> And yet (notwithſtandinge theſe louinge admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions and warninges geuen vnto you (not by lighte preachers) but by Chriſte hymſelfe, and by his Apoſtles) theſame doctrines be dayly taughte, preached / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and malitiouſlye defended with you.</p>
            <p>Therfore haue I accordinge to my bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dutie, ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth, that you might beware of them, and of the preachers of them. So that ye maye auoyde the plage of God that hangeth ouer vs, for oure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partinge from Chriſte, and from his true doctrines vnto the ſeruice and obedience of Antichriſte and of his falſe doctrines / which be mere and plaine contrary to Chriſte and his doctrines. By the which condition and ſure marke, youre lordſhips maye well knowe them euer.</p>
            <p>And bycauſe I haue reherſed ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Antichriſtes falſe doctrines, that al men maye wel diſcerne and iudge the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of his falſe doctrines by them that I haue here written. I will now directe my penne to expreſſe and declare, a certen aſſured ſigne and token geuen by Daniel
<pb facs="tcp:17381:24"/>
and alſo by Chriſte, of the tyme wherin Antichriſt ſhuld come and rage againſte Chriſte,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> Chriſte warneth vs to loke for him when we ſhall ſe abhomination of deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtande in the holy place. For the true declaration of the which texte, it is to be noted, honorable lordes, that the Apoſtle calleth vs the temple of God ſayenge:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> The temple of God is holy, which be you Conſideringe that we be the temple of God, and the holy place. What more abhomination of deſolation can ther be in the holy place, then to exile God out of his temple and holy place, not only by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workinge of manifolde ſinnes, fylthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and deteſtable wickednes, wherof was neuer moare plentie vſed: but alſo in the ſtede of God to receaue Antichriſte the men of ſynne, and childe of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as Paul nameth hym? Is not this to put man in Gods ſtede, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we truſt to receaue remiſſion of ſinnes and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe of the Romiſh Antichriſte, and that in perchmeyne ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideringe that we heare not him preach any goſpell to vs, wherby oure ſinnes ſhuld be forgeuen vs, nor yet knoweth he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our ſinnes? If he can forgeue vs oure ſinnes, without hearinge oure ſinnes nombred vnto him; and without
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17381:24"/>
ſpeakinge with vs, wherfore wyl not our prieſtes forgeue vs oure ſinnes excepte they muſt heare them tolde in to their ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? Is not this abomination of deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtandinge in the holy place? To geue ouer oure truſt and confidence that we oughe to haue of remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of oure ſinnes, at Gods handes for Chriſtes ſake only, and now to haue confidence to haue it at Antichriſtes handes (for a litle money) that is moſt contrary to God &amp; to Chriſte in all thinges? Oh moſt abomination of deſolation, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge in mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that ſhulde be the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of God, and the dwellinge place of the holy gooſt. Is it not a foule abomination of deſolation ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge in the holy place? In the ſtede of Chriſtes only one ſacrifice which he made of himſelfe to God his father for vs vpon the croſſe, now to ſet vp a new ſacrifice to be made to God for vs of a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of bread and a cuppe of wyne, and to lyfte vp them to be ſhewed to the people, to be gaſed vpon and to be worſhipped, and not to be receaued, and to be eaten &amp; dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken, accordinge to Chriſtes inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and commaundemente? Is it not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination of de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge in the holy church of God in the ſtede of the goſpell to be preached and declared
<pb facs="tcp:17381:25"/>
vnto the people in ſoch maner that they mighte receaue comforte and hope ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to haue the goſpell and other partes of the holy ſcriptures / to be read &amp; ſonge in a ſpeache nether vnderſtanded not knowen of the hearers of them?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.</note>Sainte Paul ſayeth / what ſo euer was written, was written for our doctrine and learninge, that thorow patience and conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy ſcriptures we mighte receaue hope. But Antichriſt hath ordeyned a payne ſownde, to occupie the eares of the people callinge it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, although therbe no interpretation or de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claration therof made to the people.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.</note> For he &amp; his filthie ſecte well knowe that the Apoſtle ſayeth, that all thinges that be declared &amp; opened bringe lighte. Which Antichriſte &amp; his filthy generation maye not ſuffer nor abydes becauſe their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> which be al wycked and done in dar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes ſhuld by the lighte he made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the world. For euen as Chriſte came an to the world to geue light to the world: Euen ſo is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte came in to the world, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light that Chriſt broughte in to the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note>The Apoſtle commaundeth that what ſo euer be done in the church, that it ſhould
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17381:25"/>
be done to the inſtruction and edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the congregation. For ſayeth he, yf any man ſpeake with tonges, let it be by two or thre at the moſte, and that by order, &amp; let one interpretate or declare. And yf ther be no man there to let him kepe ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſpeake not to the congregacion. Do not your lordſhips perceaue plainly how Antichriſte &amp; his filthy generation ſtudy and laboure with policy to ſubuerte all godly and profitable ordinaunces made by Chriſt and by his Apoſtles? Wherfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Paules doctrine and the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinaunces receaued, do ye ſuffer our prieſtes to reade a ſynge the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures dayly in the churches to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, in a tonge that they vnderſtande not, nor perceaue that is ſpoken calling it Gods ſeruice, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelling the people to come to heare it? Who vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth or is taught any thinge therby? They mocke the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a vayne ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, wherby they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no luſt, nor commoditie, nor profite.</p>
            <p>Is not this Antichriſtes ordinaunce of the holy ſcriptures to be reade in a tonge or ſpeche nor vnderſtande nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that commaundeth that the worde of God ſhuld dwel in vs abundauntly, that
<pb facs="tcp:17381:26"/>
we mighte teach the one the other: A wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull crafty abomination of deſolation ſtanding in the holy place, depriuinge the people of the vnderſtandinge of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures? And where Chriſte hath ordened certen Apoſtles, certen prophetes, ſome Euangeliſtes and doctours to fyniſh a nomber of the electe, and to buylde the miſticall body of Chriſte. In the ſtede of which miniſters of Chriſte by Antichriſte are entred in theues that receaue and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke greate reuenuwes and profites of the benefices: but they do no thinge the office that Chriſte appointed and aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto the office to be done. Euen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueninge wolfes that nether ſpare nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the flocke of Chriſte. And no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayl it is, for in that they take the profites of their benefices, and do not the office ther vnto belonginge, by Chriſtes ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they be theues by daye and by nighte.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10.</note> Whoſe office and cominge, is not to fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and to fauoure the flocke (ſayeth Chriſt) but to ſteale, to kyll, and deſtroye, as your lordſhips haue therof to moch experience, and moſt certen profe.</p>
            <p>Is it not therfore abomination of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation ſtandinge in the holy place, to ſee a thefe and a murtherer ſtande in the church of God in the ſteade of a true and
<pb facs="tcp:17381:26"/>
diligente paſtoure and godly feader or biſſhop? Is it not abomination of deſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſtandinge in the chief cytie of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, to ſea franked fat Boore ſittinge at euery ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preached at Pauls croſſe, and theſame not be founde ones in the yere in the ſame pulpet, feadinge the floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke committed to his ſpirituall charge? Is it not abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of deſolation ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge in the holy place, to ſe the holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in oure natiue Engliſh tonge writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon euery wall in the churches, now to be by commaundemente blotted out and in the ſtede therof erected kerued ymages of wood and of ſtone, by Gods owne ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence accurſed, and all they that make the ſame? And how they that cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſet vp ſhall eſcape the ſame curſe. I know not. They alſo vpon palmes ſondaye lifte vp a cloth and ſaye, hayle oure kynge, to a Roode made of a wooden blocke. Doutles, a worthy kinge for ſoch a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Now (right honorable Lordes) I truſt ye be not ignorante of the tyme wherin Antichriſte ſhall come, regne and rage againſte God and Chriſte. Euen verely now, when there was neuer moare abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation ſtanding in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s conſcience, and erected and ſet vp in the
<pb facs="tcp:17381:27"/>
temple and church of God. Where as, in the ſtede of a conſtante fayth in Chriſt, is planted a moſt wicked faith &amp; truſt in the man of ſinne. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes only one ſacrifice made vnto for vs for euer ſufficiently, is erected and ſet vp a ſacrifice made of bread and wyne, day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be made a ſacrifice for vs. And in the ſtede of the holy ſcriptures to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that the people might vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſence and meaninge therof, is erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeyned the goſpels and holy ſcriptures to be read and ſpoken in a tonge and ſpeache that the people which heare the voyce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no profite or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte therby. By this pointe of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination of Deſolation, all the clergie for forth them ſelfes that they abhorre no thinge moare then the lighte of Gods worde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> Which no man doeth, but he that doeth euill, ſayeth Chriſte that lyeth not.</p>
            <p>In the ſtede of paſtours and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al teachers, be entred in theues and moſt cruel murtherers. And in the ſtede of the holy ſcriptures written vpon the church walles in a ſpeach that the people do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and perceaue, be erected and ſet vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erued ymages, accurſed of God with the makers of them. So that in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17381:27"/>
ſtede of lighte and knowlege, is brought in and traded darknes and ignorancie which he the greateſt policies and ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le craftes practiſed by Antichrifle and by all his filthy ſecte, wherby, he and they maye bringe ſoules to hell.</p>
            <p>Now it reſteth to be noted (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable lordes (wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle nameth Antichriſt the man of ſinne, rather then a ſinner, as al men be conceiued, and borne in ſinne. Paul nameth him the man of ſinne, becauſe from him, as from a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne and heed well ſpringe, floweth and ſpringeth all notable and greate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wickednes: as falſe doctrines, wicked lawes and decrees, diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſations for buggery, fornication, and all kinde of luſt and lechery, for Symony and vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Wherby all men be drawen and leade from their faith in God and in Chriſte, in to a falſe faith and truſt in moſt vayne tryfles and vanities, wherby he practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to bringe innumarable ſoules to hell.</p>
            <p>Alſo right honorable lordes, where as God hath commaunded all men to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediente to the higher powers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2</note> as to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges moſt excellente, or to ſoch as be ſet in authoritie. Notwithſtanding ſoch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement geuen from God, yet Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:17381:28"/>
myndinge to declare himſelfe and his ſecte to be aduerſaries to God and Chriſte, hath reſiſted and circumuented many Emperours &amp; alſo kinges, whome thorow moſt deteſtable treaſon, ſedition and inteſtine warre in their Empires, Realmes and dominions, he hath depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and depriued of their Empires and kingedomes, to the great diſhonour and diſoledie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of moch chriſten blood, &amp; the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table deſolation of many wydowes, and miſerable orba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of many Orphanes and fatherles childerne. As the depoſition of Chelperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus beinge French kynge from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who was naturally borne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the noble lynage and houſe of the kinges of Fraunce, and in his ſtede the erectinge and makinge kinge Pipinus, which was not borne of any noble houſe, nor of the lynage of kinges of Fraunce. The depoſition and putting downe the Emperours Frederike from his Empire. The depoſition alſo of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho kinge of the Longebardes, and of many other do manifeſtly beare wytnes</p>
            <p>Amongeſt the which, I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto your lordſhips memories, one lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table hiſtorie that is this. When Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich the fourth Emperour of that name,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:28"/>
attempted to haue the electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh biſhop, as his noble progenitours before him had. One Hyldibra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke beinge then the Romiſh biſhop, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him ſelfe Gregory the ſeuenth biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ther of that name, did fearſly withſtande the ſaid Henrich &amp; ſtered vp ſoch inteſtine ſedition and warres in his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, that his people did ſeke mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to choſe a new Emperoure / which treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, beinge forſene of the ſaid Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and of his counſaill, his enimies could not bring their wicked enterpriſe and purpoſe to effecte. Then the ſaid Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kiſh pope Gregorie (whoſe couetou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnes, ambition, and pride, all the Italian writers can worthelie teſtifie, Amongeſt whom Beno the cardinal, moſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; plainly paynteth and ſetteth forth the ſame) excomunicated the ſaid Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich and as many as did either ayde him with power riches or vitailes, And did forther abſolue and diſcharge al the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of the ſaid Henrich of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towardes him, which they by Gods lawes did owe vnto the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroure. And then, in open proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made in all the dominions of the ſaid Henrich, he burdened and ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſaid Henrich with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt odious
<pb facs="tcp:17381:29"/>
and greuous title and name, Heretike<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſchiſmatike, enemie to God and to all holy church, wherby many of his fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and ſubiectes (euen al they in whoſe conſciences did ſitte Antichriſte, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienge Gods holy place) did flie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from the ſaid Emperoure. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the power of the ſaid Emperoure was greatlye decayed and miniſhed. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hildibrande the monkiſh Pope beſtered him buſylie, and cauſed one Rodulph duke of Sweuclande to be elected Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: Who after great bloodſhedinge loſt his lyfe and Empire. After him, by Gregories commaundemente one Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Earle of Lucenburge was choſen Emperour, who after great ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlaghter was ſleyne in the warres and loſt his life and Empire. And thridly thorow treaſon wrought by Gregorie, was one Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio Echerte choſen to be Emperour, who after greate ſlaghter of chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſt not only his Empire but alſo his lyfe, which cruell warres finiſhed, with no litle bloodſheding gaue occaſion to other princes, to feare to fyght againſte the ſaid Henrich, becauſe of the great murther and deeth of theſe thre noble princes. But yet the malice and cruell am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bition of the hearte of that monkiſh pope
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17381:29"/>
Gregory, coulde not be pacified, but that for his priuate lucre &amp; honour he wolde maynteyne ſo blody warres, neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge moued to mercye nor pitie with the deſtruction of ſo many cities and tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſet a fyre and myſerably waſted, nor with the deſtruction, treadinge downe and vtter waſte made of ſo many feldes of corne and graſſe, nor yet with the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of ſo moch chriſten blood, nor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lamentacion and mourninge of ſo many widowes for their huſbandes ſley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, nor with the greuous outerye of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes that dyed for lacke of bodylye foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, nor for anye euill that enſueth the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious warres, wold this holy father leaue of his workinge of ſedition and treaſon.</p>
            <p>Oh horrible monſter? Againſte na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he ſtered vp Henrich the only ſonne of Henrich the fourth to gather a great army againſt his owne naturall father, who nether for publike nor priuate wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge done by his father to him, noe any other euil was prouoked therto. Neuertheleſſe he did not only vnnaturally forſake his father, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>draw his ayde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his father in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of neade, but thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treaſon wroughte by Gregorie &amp; by his helpe he circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented his father and oppreſſed him
<pb facs="tcp:17381:30"/>
with power, did take him priſoner in the warres, and leed him captiue to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, where he put his awne father myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablye to death.</p>
            <p>Behold, right honorable Lordes, a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedie moare then cruell and bloody. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the charitie of oure holy fathers of Rome: By this facte they haue ſetforth ſoch exemple of wickednes, as neuer was before ſeene or hearde of. If their ſedition, treaſon, oppreſſion, craftes and ſubtelties be well wayed and pondered of all wicked men they maye moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie be called, not only a wicked ſynner, but alſo the man of ſinne. From whome all the deteſtable and great ſinnes of the world procede although there ſhuld not be had in remembrance all their diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations for the ſtewes of whoriſh wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and of fylthy and abhominable Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitical luſtes, for Symonye, vſurye, and all other vices to regne in the worlde.</p>
            <p>Now, righte honorable lordes, I truſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſufficiently ſet forth this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrus &amp; furious beaſt Antichriſt, as well by his falſe doctrines, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue not fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be falſe of myne owne brayne and phanteſye: but of the manifeſt ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of Chriſte &amp; his Apoſtles, ſo plainly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be nether obſcure, darke, nor hard to
<pb facs="tcp:17381:30"/>
be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Who alſo haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beware of them, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.</note> &amp; ſo to departe &amp; decline fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. I haue alſo ſet forth his tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, his ſedition, his treaſon, his crafty and falſe deceates, wherwith he hath cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuented, oppreſſed and deceaued, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Emperours, kinges and other noble rulers to whome Chriſt commaunded hym to obeye,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.</note> and gaue him alſo a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſte and playne example when he pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed tribute for himſelfe and Peter. And by his owne obedience vſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto the higher powers &amp; vnto their lawes. He neuer gaue him exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie or power to depoſe other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure, kinge or any other cyuil rules. And therfore for this his diſobedience towar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des God, and for all his other iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he is iuſtly called the man of ſinne, a child of eternal perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that he is worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a beaſt, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tike madde man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer was madde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ether wil ſaye or thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is other. Chriſtes vicare, or ſucceſſoure to the Apoſtle. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the deuels vicar and ſucceſſoure, or clothe deuel himſelfe. For as by the frute the tree is moſt certenly knowen, euen ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, your lordſhips, by theſe his falſe doctrines &amp; al other his wickednes,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:31"/>
aſſuredly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man of ſynne veraye Antichriſte himſelfe: And all his wicked generation to be the ſectes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the wicked brood of Antichriſte, moſt contrary to God and Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Wherfore he moſt falſly vſurpeth to him the title and name of holy father, or of Chriſtes vicar in earth, or ſucceſſoure of the Apoſtles. But moch more worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly is called Antichriſt the moſt malitious enemie and hatefull aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Chriſt, as both his doctrines, his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crees &amp; wicked lawes, his pride exaltinge him ſelfe aboue al Emperours &amp; kinges, his diſpenſational for ſinne to be vſed in the church of God, his vanities where with he deludeth and bewytcheth the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all his forged and fayned ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, his hypocriſis, diſſimulation, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, treaſon, moſt ſeuere crueltie, and all other his wickednes and moſt deteſtable lyſt of both hym and all his fluttiſh gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſerpentes, and filthy ſecte of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideles do manifeſtly proue and teſtifie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men. So that doubtles, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can not be any thinge more contrary to God and Chriſte, then he himſelf and his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked broede do in all thinges.</p>
            <p>Conſideringe that youre lordſhipe be not now ignoraunce (as my truſt is what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17381:31"/>
thinge Antichriſt is, but that you wel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and knowe that all they that be come in to the church to occupie an mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, office or vocation contrary to Gods worde and Chriſtes ordinaunce and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointementes, or abuſe his ſacramentes contrarye to his ordinaunces, or that teach any falſe doctrine, or that take vpon them any of Chriſtes honoure or power, be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raye Antichriſtes, which is as moch to ſaye as againſte Chriſte.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, right honorable lordes, I hope that God will open the eyes of your heartes that you maye nowe at the laſt ſee and well perceaue, by what crafte, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed and ſubtile deuyſes, you haue ben deceaued, &amp; entiſed to ſerue Antichriſt in the ſtede of Chriſte: the deuel in the ſtede of God: to folowe falſe ſuperſtition, in the ſtede of Chriſtes true religion: hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and vanitie, in the ſtede of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten veritie. And in concluſion, that you maye well vnderſtande, that you of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, haue ben moſt blinded in your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, moſt fylthilie corrupted, and your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge and ſenſes moſt ſhamfully deluded, begyled and bewitched.</p>
            <p>Therfore, my good Lordes, nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe youre wits and vnderſtandinges. And knowe you certenly that all your
<pb facs="tcp:17381:32"/>
lordly lorde biſſhops be of the naturall broede of Antichriſte. Who with all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie policie and falſheed ſtudie and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to obſcure the light of Gods worde,<note place="margin">why they make the nobles par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>takers.</note> and to ſubuerte the ordenaunces of Chriſt and of his Apoſtles and obſtinatly defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their errours and euill doinges and make you their miniſters to murther your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern for their faith, againſt your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to wrappe you and your poſteritie in Gods diſpleaſure with them.</p>
            <p>And becauſe your lordſhips ſhall not be deceaued in them. I haue geuen you the comon token ſigne and marke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you &amp; al men can not but know them to be againſt Chriſt and his worde. Where Chriſte ſayde to Peter, feede, feede, feede, Which is to ſaye: teach, teach, teach. They take teachinge for no parte of their office, but only to multiplie a ſorte of blinde cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, to bringe the people from know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage of Chriſte, and to kepe them vnder in ignorance with crueltie, And that they maye bringe that to paſſe, they laboure to be lordes and to haue temporal offices contrary to Gods worde ſayenge. The kinges of the nations reigne ouer them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 22</note> and they that beare rule ouer them be called gratious lordes. But you ſhall not be ſo. That is you ſhall not take upon
<pb facs="tcp:17381:32"/>
you to haue ciuill gouernaunce and rule ouer the people, ne yet to be called gratious lordes. S. Peter commaundeth all biſhops and ſoch as haue ſpirituall charge of ſoules committed to them, to feede the flocke of Chriſte willingly (as Chriſte commaunded him) and not to be lordes ouer the pariſhes, but euen as they were one of the flocke.</p>
            <p>Yet your lordſhips well perceaue that oure biſhops, not only take to them ſelfes the name of lorde and gratious lorde: but alſo procure to haue both cyuell gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and rule ouer the people, as to be Lorde chaunceloure, Lorde preſidente, and to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearinge of teſtamentary cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of whoredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, of dyuorſes, of ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, which be no ſpirituall matters Except a man will ſo call them, bycauſe that they that boaſt to be ſpirituall only, do moſt vſe them. And as for preachinge (where with Chriſte chiefly chargeth his miniſters) is the leaſt poynte of their charge. But they muſt atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> byſſhoppinge of childern, chriſteninge of belles, of churches &amp; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyardes, altares, and ſoch other baggage and abominations as were neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of Chriſte, nor yet practiſed not knowen of his Apoſtles. Wherby they maye eaſlye be knowen not to be of Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:17381:33"/>
but againſt Chriſt and very Antichriſtes.</p>
            <p>In lyke maner the perſones, vicars, and curates, that are admitted by them to haue, enioye and occupie, the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and profite of any ſpiritual benefice wherunto perteyneth cure and charge of ſoules, do not diligently reache the Lawe &amp; the Goſpell, but noſell the people with longe Matenſes, Maſſes and Euen ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tonge. And where ryche pariſſhes be they rocke them with mirrye ſinginge and pipinge with ſoch guega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes to pleaſe them withall, cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to Gods worde and Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, which ſayeth. As my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent me,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 20.</note> euen ſo do I ſende you. But his Father dyd ſende him to preache as it is playne Eſaye. 61. Mark. 1. Luke. 4. with the whiche comau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt, geuen to all that haue charge of ſoules, nother Emperoure, Kinge, nor Quene maye lawfully diſpence, or diſcharge. Wherfore as they be miniſers contrary and not according to Chriſtes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Euen ſo be they Antichriſtes, that be euer againſt Chriſt, in all his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and forme of lyuing. As Chriſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he that is not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, is againſt me.<note place="margin">Matt. 12.</note> And how many ſo euer be come againſt me be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s by daye and nighte.<note place="margin">Ioan. 10.</note> And
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17381:33"/>
conſequently. Chriſt myndinge to ſhew vnto you, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicions wherby ye maye euer know, who be ſpirituall theues ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: the thefe commeth not but to ſteale, to kill, and to deſtroye. Of their ſtealin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, youre Lordſhips be not ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te. How many beneficed men be within this Realme as well biſhops, as deanes, Archedeacons, perſons, uicars, and prebendaries which take the profites from their benefices / and do not feede their flock with the word of God?<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> with out the which the ſoules of the flocke ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not lyue. Wherfore they ſteale the profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that do not the office.</p>
            <p>And of their cruell mortheringe (you haue to moch experience) &amp; that nother of thefe, mortherere, robber, or traytour: but of the beſt lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this realme or that euer were in this realme: Euen of ſoch as were hable to reproue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trolle them in all thinges by Gods worde. Wherin they deceaue and mocke you, and all the people. And to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veraye theues, And as, youre lordſhips haue to moch experience of their ſtealin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and of their mortheringe: Euen ſo ſhal your lordſhips not ſayle to haue more certen and ſure experience, that they ſhal be moſt miſerable deſtroyers of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme
<pb facs="tcp:17381:34"/>
of Englande, and that at ſoch tyme, when your lordſhips nor any of youre poſteritie, ſhalbe hable to prouyde any helpe or remedie to redreſſe their de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction. For euen as Chriſtes wordes be vnfaynedly true that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thefe cometh not for any purpoſe but to ſteale and to kyll, ſo muſt the reſidew of his wordes, euer be founde to be true, moſt certen and ſure, that is, that he ſhall alſo deſtroye.</p>
            <p>And although you now do not regard nor beleue Chriſtes wordes to be true, yet, when you thinke leaſt theron, your infidelitie ſhalbe requyred with the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge and peynful ſufferinge the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of you, and of youre poſterytie, and the moſt miſerable chaunge and alteration of the ſtate of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme.</p>
            <p>This miſerable miſchiefe enſueth and cometh of this miſorder that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce of this realme, by your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips conſentes, hath be committed and done agaynſt God, in makinge a biſhop (that by Gods worde and appointeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te was aſſigned to feed the flocke commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his ſpirituall charge) to leaue his office, committed to hym by God to be executed and done, to be a chauncelour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17381:34"/>
wher by he was ſo occupied and buſied in the hearinge of the matters &amp; affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of this realme, that he could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende his flocke to feade them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to Chriſtes commaundemente. Wherby he was put out of that order and rule that God had appointed to him. Beinge out of the which order &amp; appointemente of God, he could neuer be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modietie or profite to this realme. For he was entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office not by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dore Chriſt, but aſcended by a nother waye, &amp; therfore was a thefe, from<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e no good counſaill or any other godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes can procede, nor more then of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maye grapes be gadered. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his doinges will proue to well. For in that office he hath brought to paſſe by his counſaill and perſuaſion, and by your lordſhips ſufferau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, ſoch incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable euill, that all Englande ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente and bewayle the ſame. Not only in kyllinge the preachers and lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this realem, but alſo in the vtt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r deſtruction of this Realme, &amp; the altera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſtate and honour of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And although God hath delyuered you of that ſpirituall thefe. Yet be your lordſhips and all the Realme burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a nother in the ſame office,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:35"/>
that ſhall do no leſſe euil then the other hath done. Yf ſo moch euill maye be done. For as a ioynte ordeyned by God in the bodye, is appointed and ſet in a dew order to helpe the bodie, which ioynte beinge out of that order that God hath ſet it in, can not be any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie and helpe to the bodie, but great peyne and trouble to the bodye. Euen in lyke maner, if a biſhop, that is appointed and ordeyned by God to teach his flocke, be taken from that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice wher in God had aſſigned and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him: he can neuer be profitable but great hurte and peyne to the bodie. For I thinke that there is no man that hath any knowlege in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or any good conſcience towarde God, but he well knoweth that a biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop that feedeth not his flocke is a thefe. Otherwiſe he beleueth not Chriſte to be true in his wordes, And if he be a thefe (as the trueth ſayeth he is) then is his cominge for no nother purpoſe, then to ſteale, to kyll and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye. And who ſo euer doubteth ther of, doubteth whether Chriſte be true.</p>
            <p>And I feare me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours haue not beleued Chriſte to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17381:35"/>
true, that they ſhall proue it true by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, to their great peyne. Soch ſhalbe the frutes of a biſhop ſet in autoritie to be a counſelour for the temporall affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the Realme, that he is one of them that is come to ſteal, to kill and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye. Of whome God by his prophete Eſai, complayneth ſayenge:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.</note> Heare oh heauens, and herken oh earth, for the Lorde ſpeaketh. I haue noreſhed and brought vp childerne, and they are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye from me. How happeneth it that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous citie which was ful of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is become vnfaithful as an whore? Rightuouſnes dwelled in her, but now mortherers. In tymes paſt, it was the office of Nero and of other tyrantes to tormentt men to death for their faith: but now oure engliſh biſhops haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to put the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes out of that office. For they them ſelfes condemne both lerned and vnlerned for their faith, and make you, right honorable lordes, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the office. That they might ſet forth to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they be the veraye theues, of whom Chriſt (that can not lie) ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Whoſe cominge is for no nother purpoſe then to ſteale, to kill, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye.</p>
            <p>And yet to deceaue the people, they
<pb facs="tcp:17381:36"/>
be crepte in vnder the cloke of my lorde biſhop, a reuerende father. But to this my lorde biſſhops and their accompliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes ſaye: that they kil none for their fayth but for their hereſie, which ought of all Chriſten men to be abhorred and auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, accordinge to the true ſaye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of the Apoſtle, that commaundeth ſayenge an heretike, after he is twiſe reproued auoyd him.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.</note> But yet ſayeth he not kil min, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd him. As al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primatiue church haue ſhewed manifeſt example in the exile of many that in veraye dede were heretikes approued by gods worde to be heretikes, and yet were not perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to deeth for their hereſyes Vntil An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt of Rome the heed of al heretikes by crafte, gyle and falſheed ſeduced and begyled the Emperours and kinges, and robbed them of their dominions and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, wherby the hath exalted him ſelfe not only aboue them, but alſo aboue God.</p>
            <p>And then became he a moſt cruell ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and made lawes of death, for all ſoch as he and his fylthy ſecte did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuge heretikes, Therby colourably to morther and deſtroye, all ſoch as did ones ſpeake or preach againſt his vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power, or by any meanes reueyle his
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17381:36"/>
iniquitie for that calleth he and all his fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye generation of infideles hereſie.</p>
            <p>Which exemple of makinge of lyke lawes oure engliſh biſhops did compaſſe and bringe to paſſe about the yere of oure Lorde 1420. then beinge a biſhop Lorde Chaunceloure and a nother lorde priuey Seale, wherby being in great authoritie &amp; high eſtimation amongeſt the nobles and counſelours thorow flattery circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented the kinge, and his counſaill, and other of the nobles to make a law in Englande to ſuppreſſe hereſie ſpronge vp in this realme. But what that hereſie was that muſt only be adiudged, by the Antichriſtes lawes and by his ſworen ſecte the generation of infideles, the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of God &amp; aduerſaries of Chriſte. For as it is reported by cronicles, it was the reuelation of Antichriſtes iniquitie, that he calleth hereſye.</p>
            <p>Forther to colour their cruel tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie, they ſayed with their forfathers the Biſhops, Prieſtes, Scribes, and Phariſeys, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the Iewiſh clergie: It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to vs for to ſley any man. And as for vs, ye may truſt well inough, we be to holy to deceaue you. You maye frely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſcrupuloſitie of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, crucifie whome ſo euer we committe in to voure handes.
<pb facs="tcp:17381:37"/>
For if he be not an euill doer, we wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deliuer him vnto you. Youre ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours neade neuer to examine the cauſe, but boldly burne him. Oure ſoules for youres. His blood vpon oure heades. And by ſoch ſubtile meanes made all Kinges, and Officers of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that haue bin ſynce, their tourmentours, and hange me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A goodly office that they haue ſett all kinges and you, right honorable lordes, in. They haue made the kinge and you their hange men, &amp; not a whit better. And yet for al their warrantyſe &amp; putti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their ſoules for youres, &amp; though ye waſh neuer ſo cleane your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pylate. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye thus morther the innocentes for their ſaith in Ieſu Chriſte, be aſſured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods curſe will not departe from you &amp; youre howſes excepce ye ſpedelye repente.</p>
            <p>But how that law agreeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods worde it ſhal appere. Euen as God &amp; the deuel, Chriſt, and Antichriſt, light, and darkenes. Firſt God by his Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſai.</hi> 11.</note> they ſhal not hurte, nor ſhall they kil in all my holy hyll. By this holy hil, meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g this his church. Wherfore yf youre lordly Lorde biſhops were true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtres in this church, they wold not mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther any man for his faith / or for want of a good faith, which he can not haue of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17381:37"/>
his awne power and ſtudie. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Hieremie ſayeth alſo:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 7.</note> Behold theſe men ſaye vnto me, where is the worde of the Lorde. Let it come. Where as I neuer the leſſe leading the flocke in thy wayes, haue compelled no man by violence, for I neuer deſired mans deeth. This kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt thou well. Here Hieremie ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he leading the flocke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, compelled none by violence to walke therin. This doctrine and exemple geuen by Hieremie agreeth but ſclenderlye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Antichriſtes canons, decrees, &amp; lawes, nor with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law newly reuyued by your lordſhips conſentes, and laſte of all with youre biſhops mortheringe and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge of your lerned men.</p>
            <p>Alſo when Chriſte going vnto Hieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem, Ioan and Iames entered in to a citie of the Samaritanes to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for Chriſte. But the citeſins wold not receaue Chriſt. Wherfore Ioan and Iames retourned to Chriſt, and ſhewed to him the vnkindnes of the citeſins ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng vnto him: Maſter will thou that we commaundye fyre to come from heauen, and conſume them? Ieſus turned to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and rebuked them ſayenge: You know not of what ſpirit ye be. The ſonne of man is not come to deſtroye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s lyues,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:38"/>
but to ſaue them.</p>
            <p>If your lordly lorde biſſhops were Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes true ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, then wold they folow his doctrine and example. As Chriſt ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth. He that ſerueth me, let him folow me.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12.</note> And he that foloweth me walketh not in darknes. But all men maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that this their mortheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, is mere contrary to both Chriſtes doctrine and example, and vtterly bewrayeth them to be the ſeruantes of Antichriſte. As Paul ſayeth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.</note> Good deades be manifeſte, and they that be euyll can not be hid.</p>
            <p>The parable of Chriſte of the tares ſowed by the enemie vpon the good ſeed which the maſter wold not haue drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp vntill harueſte (leſte drawinge vp the tares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> the good wheate ſhuld alſo haue ben drawen vp) declareth manifeſtlie, that Chriſte wold not any man of an euil faith, to be killed for his euill faith. For if Paul had byn tormented to deeth, for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of a good faith, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequuter of Chriſtes church. He the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had neuer bin the Apoſtle of the gentiles, ne yet the moſt laborious worke man that euer wrought in Chriſtes vinyard. And if Sainte Auguſtine had fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſo cruell tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to haue perſequuted him to deeth before he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted by God at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinge
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17381:38"/>
of S. Ambroſe: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church had wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed at this daye, as godly a doctor &amp; wryter as euer wrote in Chriſtes church ſence the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>But ouer &amp; beſides Chriſtes doctrine and exmple, which be not any errours or vperfite doctrines, the Apoſtles doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine is: that the ſeruante of God ſhulde not ſtryue,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2</note> but to be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle to al men apte to teach, and one that can ſuffer, the euill with mekenes, and can enforme them that reſiſte the trueth. He ſayeth not, can kill them that reſiſte the trueth, but can enforme them. For neither he nor nay ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can know when it ſhall pleaſe God to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the eyes of his heart, and to geue vnto him a perfite faith, which now ys holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> captiue in vnbelefe, at the wil of the Lorde. This doctine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you wil not geue credite therto, yet proueth it manifeſtly before all men that your lordly lorde biſhops be not the ſeruauntes of God, that ſhuld ſuffer the euill accordinge to Chriſtes doctrine and example. And alſo this doctrine of the Apoſtle proueth, that youre law reuyued, is againſt the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Chriſte and of his Apoſtle, And therfore is a wicked law inuented by Antichriſte, and his filthy genratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:39"/>
and ſluttiſh ſecte of infideles, to ſubuert &amp; extinguiſh al godly knowleage &amp; faith.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Apoſtle ſayethrif ther be any that obeyeth not oure teachinges,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3</note> ſende vs worde of him by a letter and haue no company with him that he may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And counte him not as an enemie: but warne him as a brother. Perceaue ye not, honorable lordes, how contrary your biſhops be to Chriſte, and how con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie they be to his doctrine, and to the doctrine of his Apoſtles, and alſo how wicked your law lately by your conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes reuyued is, contrary to Gods worde?</p>
            <p>But good my lordes, thinke not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you can gather grapes vpon thornes. This their mortheringe of their brethern for their faith, declareth vnto all men (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vnderſtandinge is not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye by God) that they be the theues of which Chriſte ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.</note> of whome ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not come any good frute. For morther is a worke that proueth them to be the deuels ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, who was a mortherer from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginninge, ſayeth Chriſt that lyeth not. But as Abraham had two children, one borne after the fleſhe called Iſmael,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</note> and an other after the ſpirite called Iſaac. As then he that was borne carnally perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him that was borne ſpirituallye, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:17381:39"/>
ſo is it now ſayeth Sainte Paul</p>
            <p>Did Chriſt, my good lordes, compel any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come to his religion, with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonemente, or with fyre? Did Chriſte kill the Iewes, ſcribes, &amp; phariſees that hearinge his doctrine, and ſeinge alſo his wonderous miracles, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge both wold not beleue in him? Ys not faith, honorable lordes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only gifte of God, liberally geuen to whome it plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth him? Can any man by his awne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, ſtudie, and laboure obteyne faith? If you will ſuffer youre byteſhepes ſo cruelly to morther men for wante of ſoch faith as it hath pleaſed them to deuyſe, by lyke equitie and Reaſon maye you ſuffer them to morther all them that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not the lyberall gifte of God to make whole the ſicke. And alſo with moare equitie you your ſelfes maye hange vp the biſhop of London and all youre other biſſhops &amp; preiſtes as theues and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, that take charge of ſoules &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the profites of their benefices, which haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifte of God to preach the goſpell to the flocke, accordinge to Chriſtes commaundemente. And by no leſſe equitie, all they muſt ſuffer deeth that haue not the gift of chaſtitie, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to deceaue the people, they ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:17381:40"/>
they haue auowed it.</p>
            <p>And although, your lordſhips, as ye thinke, do not any violence againſt ſoch as now ſuffer by force of that wicked law, that by youre conſentes is reuiued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your lordſhips haue referred al the determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of hereſie vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your byteſhepes. Yet, be your lordſhips and all they that haue conſented to the reuiuinge and makinge in force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the ſayd law, gyltie of the blood and deeth of all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue ſuffered deeth, ſhall ſuffer or do ſuffer, by force &amp; s;tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of the ſaid law. For not only all they that committe &amp; do euill be worthy deeth (ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Paul) but alſo all they that conſente therto.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> Not only becauſe the law by force wherof many ſuffer deeth was reuyued by your conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. But alſo bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame law is manifeſt wicked &amp; vnrightuous becauſe it is contrary to the worde of God. Wherfore it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be but wicked. And therfore the ſame law wherby all they ſuffer vniuſtlie, and the blood of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſuffer deeth, ſhalbe a witnes before God againſt you of their tormentes and deeth. And then good, my lordes, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence of God pronounced againſt al them that ſhede innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te blood vnrightuouſly, not only that they be mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therers,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17381:40"/>
who ſhal neuer inheret y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heauen.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Gene.</hi> 9</note> But alſo the holy gooſt ſayeth: he that ſhedeth innocente blood of men, his blood ſhalbe ſhed againe by men.</p>
            <p>If your lordſhips do not thinke God falſe in his promiſes, loke moſt certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly for your blood (if ye do not vnfaynedly &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely repente) to be ſhed of men againe.</p>
            <p>And although you wold, not beleue the promiſes of God to be true. Yet way you the late experience of that trueth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refied in the late dukes of Somerſet and Northumberlande, whoſe doinges to al them that did know them, do manifeſtlie prooue the ſayed promiſes of God to be moſt certenly and truely verefied in them. As they can not be otherwiſe in all men.</p>
            <p>And now, I truſt your lordſhips do well vnderſtande and perceaue, that this law by your conſentes lately reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; made a law in force and ſtength, is contrary both to the doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſte and of his Apoſtles and Prophetes. Wherfore it can not be but a wicked law.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esai.</hi> 10.</note> Woo therfore be vnto you that make wicked lawes, ſayeth God by his prophe Eſaias,</p>
            <p>And if a nother magiſtrate ſhuld (by
<pb facs="tcp:17381:41"/>
the prouiſion of God) be called to reigne oue vs, who iudgeth the forme of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion laſt receaued of vs, to be contrary to Gods worde, and therfore to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely aboliſhed, then maye he perſecute all youre biſhops and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that now haue conſented to morther chriſten men for their fayth, but nor becauſe he perceaueth that they haue no perfite faith, or els a wicked faith (for then ſhould he commit lyke iniquitie) but becauſe the worde of God ſayeth: The ſame meaſure that you haue meaſured to other, the ſame ſhalbe meaſured to you againe. By this ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, that is no wicked law, al youre mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theringe biſhops maye iuſtly be handles as they haue handled them.</p>
            <p>This law of late, by youre conſentes, reuyued and made in force and ſtrength as a perfite law, doeth not only reproue youre lordſhips of youre inconſtauncie, who not longe tyme before vpon reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and godly cauſes, wel wayed, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſputed and reaſoned, did dyſanull, make fruſtrate &amp; voyed the ſame as a wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked law: but alſo this youre ſodeine rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge of the ſame, declareth, that you care not what you do, be it neuer ſo wicked &amp; contrary to God, ſo that you maye auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the diſpleaſure of the magiſtrate and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17381:41"/>
ſupreme eyuill gouernour. Wherby it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pereth manifeſtlie that you regarde mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the diſpleaſure of man then the diſple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſure of God. Doeth nor your lordſhips conſider that God ſaith by the prophere:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.</note> The lorde ſhall breake the bones of them that do ſtudie to pleaſe men?</p>
            <p>Halas, right honorable lordes, who har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo be witched you now, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly aye fled from Gods trueth?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</note> (Your awne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces ſo longe tyme) approui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Before whoſe eyes Ieſus Chriſt was ſo lyuely preached, and ſo faithfully ſet forth. And neuertheles now, not only his doctrine, and the true and profitable vſe of the ſacramentes, be by your conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes repelled for hereſie, but alſo Chriſt him ſelf in his holy membres and miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body moſt truelly tormented and ſlayn.</p>
            <p>Halas that foreyne nations ſhal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecre this inconſtantie to your diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours: namely to be ſo in conſtante and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inge in the principall pointes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerninge a Chriſten mans religion and faith, conſideringe that by your owne conſentes the ſame religion now by you repelled as hereſye, was by your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemes ſet forth and commaunded thorough all the Realme and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:17381:42"/>
of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to be taught, and alſo to be receaued of the people.</p>
            <p>To what trueth and to what religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on maye the ſubiectes of this realme here after cleaue, &amp; aſſuredly without waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe folow, which do perceaue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your lordſhips (contrary to youre owne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes before made and direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them) do flie and retiere from the doctrine and true vſe of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes that you in ſo litle tyme paſt did moſt worthely approue to be moſt Godly and neceſſarie to be taughte and folowed. God graunte that the come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme that now murmur and grudge at this inconſtancie and other your euil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, do not hereafter burden you with the ſame. And eſpeciallye for your flieng from the true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men approue to be moſt godly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> From the which ye be now fled to the great diſhonoure of God. Wherfore God by his Prophete threatneth you to bring you to diſhonoure ſayenge. I will geue them honour that honoure me. And they that diſhonoure me,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</note> them will I bringe to diſhonoure. This promiſe will God kepe with you. God therfore grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you grace truly to repente in ſeaſon. Amen.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:17381:42"/>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieremi.</hi> 5.</bibl>
               <p>Horrible and greuouſe thinges be done in the lande. The preachers teache falſly, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſtes folow them, and my people haue pleaſure therin. What will come therof at the laſt?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieremi.</hi> 7.</bibl>
               <p>From the leaſt to the moſt, they hange all vpon couetouſnes. And from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete vnto the prieſt they go all about w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> falſheed and lye, and beſydes that they heale the hurte of my people with ſwete wordes ſayenge: peace, peace, when ther is no peace at al. Therfore they muſt be aſhamed, for they haue committed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omination.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieremie.</hi> 23.</bibl>
               <p>Heare not the wordes of the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that preache vnto you, and deceaue you. For they ſpeake the meaninge of their awne heartes, and not out of the mouth of the Lorde.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hieremie.</hi> 23.</bibl>
               <p>Yea the waye that men take is wicked and theyr gouernaunce is nothinge lyke the worde of the Lorde. For the preachers and the priſtes them ſelfes are polluted ypocrytes, and their wickedneſſe haue I founde in my howſe, ſayeth the Lorde.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hiere.</hi> 51.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17381:43"/>Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath benin the Lordes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des a golden cuppe that maketh all landes dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of hyr wyne haue al people dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, therfore are they out of their wittes.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hier.</hi> 51.</bibl>
               <p>Oh my people come out of Babilon, that euery man may ſaue his lyfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fear ful wrath of the Lorde</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaias. ca.</hi> 10.</bibl>
               <p>Woo be to Aſſur that is a ſtaffe of my wrath, in whoſe hande is the rod of my puniſhmente, for I ſhal ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de him amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge theſe ypocrites, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the people that ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue deſerued my diſpleaſure ſhall I ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de him, That he maye vtterly robbe them, ſpoyle them, and treade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe lyke the myre in the ſtrete. How be it his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is not ſo, nother thinketh his hearte in his faſhion. But he ymagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth only how to ouerthrow and to deſtroye moch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For he ſayth be not my princes all kinges.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17381:43"/>
            <head>The contentes of this treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 Ther is no thinge moare perilous &amp; harte to chriſten faith, then a corrupte iudgemente.</item>
               <item>2 The multitude of people ſerue Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge nor knowinge him to be Antichriſte.</item>
               <item>3 Antichriſt cometh in vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to condemne errours and herſye, wherof he &amp; his ſworen ſecte wilbe iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and therfore condemeneth veritiein the ſiede of hereſie.</item>
               <item>4 A deſcription of Chriſt and of his office.</item>
               <item>5 The reuelation of Antichriſt and of his condicion.</item>
               <item>6 The vayne thinges that Antichriſt hath ordened.</item>
               <item>7 Antichriſte erecteth a new religion wherin he breaketh Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>8 The world receaueth Antichriſt rather then Chriſte, and what is the cauſe.</item>
               <item>9 Chriſte and his Apoſtles call certen doctrines the doctrines of deuels.</item>
               <item>10 Nether biſhop nor prieſt hath any authoritie to forgyue ſynnes, but by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the goſpell.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17381:44"/>11. Anriculer confeſſion is contrary to the doctrine of Eſai.</item>
               <item>12. The prieſtes abſolution ſpoken in a ſpech not knowen of the confeſſed, can<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not profite them.</item>
               <item>13. Certen cauſes wherfore biſhops &amp; prieſtes do mayntayne whoriſh confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>14. A token geuen by Chriſt of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me when Antichriſt ſhal come.</item>
               <item>15. Diuers abominations ſtande now in the temple of God, And what is the temple of God.</item>
               <item>16. The cauſes wherfore Paul nameth Antichriſt rather the man of ſinne then a ſynner.</item>
               <item>17. How the Quenes maieſtie is cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuented to make a law to ſtabliſh the Popes vſurped power.</item>
               <item>18. What biſhops be theues, morthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and deſtroyers.</item>
               <item>19. No man ſhuld dye for his faith.</item>
               <item>20. Who be gyltie of the deeth of all them that haue ſuffred deeth by the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lawe lately reuyued &amp; made in force.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:17381:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
